The first interstellar [music] mission
to Alpha Centuri. Philillip and Matt are
here to join the moonshot mates.
>> Are we the first kid on the block or are
we now, you know, auditioning for a
membership in a cosmic club? And the
ticket to entry is, can you handle that?
>> By the time we arrive, you know, for
15,000 years, there will already have
been a colony at Alpha Centuri.
>> A PaloAlto startup called Architect Labs
just announced the world's first fully
AI designed [music] chip called Redwood.
Zero bugs on first silicon and 3.4 times
the performance per watt of Nvidia's
Jetson.
>> Is this an incredible threat to Nvidia?
Yeah, absolutely.
>> I think I know how this game ends. It
ends with
>> extremely severe extinction events
happen every 100 million years or so,
and just switching to sustainable energy
will not be enough to stop them. His
solution, [music]
satellites in space that control
temperature and massive geoengineering
[music] will be needed before it's game
over. I completely buy that with global
AI weather models and enough points of
actuation, that's a recipe for global
weather engineering, and I think we're
going to get it.
>> Now, that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> Welcome to Moonshots, everyone. Your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponential, your front row seat to the
accelerating singularity. I'm here with
my Moonshot mates. We're going to have
the Fantastic Four. We've got the
tremendous three right now. Uh Dave
Blondon, Alex Wezner, Gross, myself,
Peter D. Mandis, of course, uh where
Salem, he's held up in TSA. A funny a
funny joke. If you watched our last pod,
uh he'll be he'll be joining us shortly.
>> Do we even know what continent? I
>> I have no idea where Salem is.
>> Okay, it'll be fun to find out.
>> He's a probability function, but he'll
be joining us in a little bit. So, our
mission on this podcast is simple.
future proof you for the coming
supersonic tsunami and keep you
optimistic about this extraordinary
decade ahead. You know, we're lucky
enough to be living during the greatest
period of transformation in human
history and we want you to understand it
and not fear it. So, every week, twice a
week on this show, uh we work to show
you the future before it arrives. Uh if
you're not a subscriber yet, as always,
please hit the subscribe button. Uh we
have a lot happening and let me just
mention to you, we want to invite all of
you uh to an AMA we're doing. So we're
inviting our moonshot guests, all of
you, our moonshotters to join us on
Zoom. Uh if you go to moonshots.com,
uh you can register. We're going to be
doing this twice. Once in the morning,
uh to get everybody in Europe and Asia
and India uh and once in the evening for
those of you in the US. Uh, and during
this AMA, we're going to have a chance
to, you know, go back and forth. We
don't get a chance to answer all your
questions, and we do read them. Uh, this
is a chance to interact with you, uh,
have your questions answered and ask you
some questions about what you want
covered on this show. We get tremendous
joy specifically from being able to like
help you uh, understand where things are
going. Uh, Dave and Alex, you guys going
to plug in hot and heavy for that one,
right?
>> Better believe it.
>> Best. I mean, What do you do in the
morning? Just stretch and get ready.
>> A few journals. I don't know. We'll
[laughter] do our best.
>> Peter, can I preemptively choose
question number three?
[laughter]
>> Of course.
>> And u these are coming in in real time,
right? Completely. It's a live
conversation.
>> You know, we're going to limit the
number of people. We've got about 200
spots left. So, please uh register now
at moonshots.com.
And we invite you to join us on X. Our
handle on X is moonshots_pod.
Uh we're putting up our our recordings
there. We're putting up uh clips. So
join us on X for all the latest news.
Okay. Uh I want to share some subscriber
love. I know I read all the comments and
I hope you guys do, too. And it's pretty
pretty epic. Just going to read a few of
them here. I love this one. There's no
way to digest the amount of new
advancements without this podcast. Uh, I
agree with you. It's the only way I keep
up with everything. Another subscriber,
uh, Rock Pedro said, "Whenever one of
these gets posted, I hit pause on the
rest of my life and sit down with a cup
of coffee and my iPad." So, thank you
for that. I love this,
>> Peter. This is framing us, I guess, less
as uh CCTV for the singularity as more
as readers digest.
>> Okay. Well, I just think it's action
adventure, honestly. Um, stop, drop, and
roll said, "This pod is hitchhiker's
guide to the singularity. Brilliant
episode." I appreciate that. Two more
real quick. Uh, Cam Abroad said, "I
can't even sit down for a two-hour movie
any longer. However, I watch this
podcast end to end every time."
>> All right.
>> Yeah. And Richard
>> and Richard Consul said, you know,
highlight of my week. Please don't ever
stop.
>> Uh, I don't think we are. [laughter]
>> This is crazy. Is the claim that
>> is the claim that we're restoring the
audience attention span?
>> Yeah, it's we we keep their attention.
What's that, Dave?
>> Oh, you got to call out to the team
behind the scenes, too. The rate of
story digestion they have to get through
has gone up, you know, since we started
doing the pod maybe 10x higher now.
>> Yeah.
>> And so they've staffed up, but I mean
just the the workload that they get
through to whittle it down to the subset
because because I have, you know, that
same feeling that that comment that
second comment like I could never keep
up with everything going on without this
podcast, too. And you know, when I come
into the script to read it, it's all
been beautifully synthesized. And so I
can study up in in like an hour and a
half.
>> Dave, a lot of that team is me. I
probably spend 10 hours [clears throat]
going through two to 300 stories that
Alex puts, you know, into our chat. Uh
it's it's insane. Well, and and also
among people who do that kind of work,
you're the only one that I know of that
has a PhD in biotech and uh MIT degrees
and in biology and aeronautics and a
deep AI and computer science background.
So, I mean, like not too many people
could filter it down to the really
relevant subset the way you do. So,
thank you.
>> I mean, I love I love our chemistry and
I just want to do a shout out to uh to
our producers Nick and Dana and to Gian
and Aiden for their support on this. You
know, our our moonshot here on this pod
is to 100x our growth and to get to 10
million subscribers. You know, every
single one of you sharing this podcast
gets us closer. So, please share it.
Please subscribe. Today, we've got 10
amazing stories. Everything from OpenAI
projecting that'll reach AGI in the next
four months uh to AI designing their own
bespoke chips, nuclear rockets to Mars.
You know, as always, there's a single
through line that the singularity is
here and it's accelerating. So, buckle
up. This is another amazing week. Uh,
now, we normally close the program with
an outro video, but today we had an
incredible intro uh delivered by Steven
Renegade, and it's so good. I want to
play it to kick us off, really get us in
the mood here. All right, listen up.
This is uh Moonshots podcast intro by
Steven Renegade. Ignition.
>> Welcome back to Moonshots. [music]
>> The systems are improving themselves.
[music]
>> Robots evolving tech breaking molds and
goals. [music]
>> Longevity calling.
>> We're turning back time.
>> Abundance waves.
>> Multi-dimensional [singing and music]
brains.
Moonshot mates decoding [music]
the future of change.
>> Wasn't that great? I love it. Thank you,
Steve. All right. Now, before we get
into the news from this week, we have a
special announcement, a breaking story
on moonshots from our very own ASI, Alex
Wezner. Gross. Alex, uh, if you if you
jump in here, please, and and introduce
our two guests and tee them up for the
first Interstellar exclusive, the Ferma
explorer mission.
>> Amazing, Peter. So folks who watch the
pod faithfully may remember Philip
Johnston who was on the pod previously,
founder and CEO of StarCloud, the
orbital data center company and making
his moonshot's debut today uh co-founder
of mine with a physical super
intelligence. Matt Pines joining us and
Philip and Matt are here to join the
Moonshot mates in their I think
exclusive pod announcement. How cheesy
does that sound? of the first
interstellar mission to Alpha Centuri.
So maybe Philip and Matt, take it away.
H how are we getting to Alpha Centtory?
>> Maybe. Yeah, maybe I can describe the
mission and then I'll I'll talk a little
bit about how PSI ended up being very
pivotal in in discovering this mission
and and and Matt can talk about the the
background behind that. So, actually the
last time we were on the podcast after
we finished recording at the end, I
said, "Oh, by the way, guys, I'm uh
planning to send a spacecraft to Alpha
Centuri, and we've we're we've put some
constraints on ourselves cuz we really
want this thing to actually launch." So,
the constraints we have is we wanted to
get at least 99% of the way to Alpha
Centuri within the next 80,000 years.
And that actually minimizes your fuel.
Any longer than 80,000 is more fuel. Any
shorter than 8,000 is more fuel. The
second constraint is we want to launch
within 3 years. The third is it must
have a 1 kilogram 1U payload. And then
the last is it must cost less than $15
million to design, build, and launch
because we're basically funding it.
>> Say that again. 15 million
>> 15. Yeah. 15 which I mean is it's an
astonishing uh target to hit.
>> It's a it's a seed round for a startup
out of MIT. [laughter]
>> It's half a seed round.
You can't count that low. This is
interstellar on the cheap. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> But 80,000 years also is a little longer
than most startups.
>> That's true. [laughter]
>> Um I I'll come back to why we're doing
it in a minute, but I'll I'll just touch
on the story of how PSI came involved.
So we'd spent six months trying to
figure out a trajectory that would make
sense where the the big challenge we
wanted to do it with solar electric and
gritted iron thruster. It's the same as
like the star cloud one satellite. It's
very cheap. The problem is the further
away ray you get from the sun, the lower
the energy that you have hitting the
solar panels. So the larger the solar
panels you need. Once you get past about
Jupiter, you're getting very low amounts
of energy. You'd need huge solar panels.
And so we tried a whole bunch of things.
Jupiter flybys, slingshots towards the
sun. We had two guys from JPL look at
it. They spent a few weeks looking at
it. Couldn't come up with anything. We
had um yeah, I mean basically 6 months
of of plugging it into claw, trying
everything we could. And then Alex goes,
"Oh, you should speak to my guys at
PSI." And I was like, "Oh, yeah. Oh,
yeah. Here we go. They're gonna beat our
beat our JPL guys." So, I didn't even
reply for like a week. I didn't reply.
And then, uh, Matt followed up and he
was like, "Hey, send over the specs for
this mission you want to do again." So,
I was, "Oh, God. Okay, I'll keep Alex
happy. I'll send the specs." A week
later, they came back with the most
unbelievable report. So this um it's uh
I think they spent you know tens of
billions of tokens on this thing and
they came up with an incredibly sort of
unintuitive and innovative uh trajectory
that makes this um makes this mass and
cost budget close. So it's essentially
we spiral out from Earth and then sort
of unintuitively we fire a retrograde
burn. So we slow ourselves down to pull
ourselves in towards the sun and we do
that for about 5 years. So we do five
retrograde burns at the furthest point
from the sun and then we start doing
what they call a a perihelion burn. So
burning your thrusters as close as
possible to the sun. And they've they've
called this maneuver the perihelion pump
maneuver. Um and what it does is it
means it has two amazing advantages. One
is we're firing our thrusters at the
closest point to the sun. So we need
less mass on the solar. But the second
is it takes advantage of this orth
effect. The orth effect is the idea that
you get more energy for a given time of
thrust the faster you're going and
you're going the fastest at the
perihelion. Um so yeah, I mean honestly
it's to me incredibly impressive that
that they they came up with this and at
this point I'll hand over to Matt and he
can explain how they did this.
>> Well uh certainly serendipity. I mean
the fact that uh AWD is my co-founder
and we had this uh connection right at
the perfect time and it's been a unique
uh synchronicity uh announcing from
explore mission and this partnership
today as well as announcing you know
physical super intelligence is uh seed
fundraising and coming out of stealth on
the same day because this mission is is
the proof of concept for what we're
building here. uh as you as you
mentioned kind of these sorts of highly
technical scientific uh challenges that
are bottlenecked by humans that have
been sort of pre-trained for 22 years
post-trained in grad school or technical
positions and then they become
scaffolded and then orchestrated in
corporate academic or government
bureaucracies. Those are the rate
limiters of kind of what our scientific
and technical ambition is. Uh and that's
why we've had to have uh large scale
national institutions organize these
sorts of breakthrough grand uh
scientific and technical initiatives. eg
sending a spacecraft uh outside the
solar system. And so this is the proof
that you can have two small teams uh
both startups, one in space, one in AI
for physics uh put their respective
heads together and come up with a
mission that uh you know pushes the
boundaries of what's possible. And yeah,
we we kind of took this as a as like a
side challenge uh to throw at our our
internal tech. We have an astrophysicist
on staff, but to be honest, we were just
uh you know, prompting uh the the system
and then you know, crafting the final
product to make sure that it had the
right uh you know, graphics and plots.
Uh but other than that, it was entirely
hands-off and we were as surprised as as
Philip's team that it came up with the
the the optimal mission trajectory. We
certainly didn't load the dice, you
know, almost minimal human steering
involved and it came up with a a
trajectory that satisfied, you know,
quite strict mission constraints. And so
I think this is the the first of many
surprises uh that that we're going to
see from pointing uh AI physicists at at
these really valuable technical and
scientific challenges.
>> Alex, I want to get more into the
details, but I thought it'd be fun to
show the Fermy mission. Uh uh
>> before you before you play it, do you
mind if I just describe what's happening
because it can be a bit wacky to just
see it out of context. Um so the idea
behind the mission is um we expect to be
or we hope to be the first to leave
earth for another star but also the last
to arrive at another star. So you know
in a thousand years time let's say you
have better propulsion technology even
if it's like 20% faster which is very
conservative. By the time we arrive you
know for 15,000 years there will already
have been a colony at Alpha Centuri. And
so they'll have had time to build things
like Dyson spheres and O'Neal rings and
all the the wacky and cool things that
we see from you know that we imagine
from sci-fi. And then from there we
estimate you know with sort of basically
current propulsion technology it will
take about uh 5 to 10 million years to
settle the galaxy. And then from there
without too much effort it would take
about a billion years to get to
Andromeda. And then from there about 5
billion years to settle the local
cluster of galaxies. Um, and I'll come
back to why we're showing all of this
maybe after the video, but just so that
people are aware, that's what you're
about to see is the next five billion
years of history.
>> Oh my god.
>> Maybe it's it's worth underlining,
Philip. This is a conservative
outerbound. I I don't actually think
it'll take 5 billion years for humanity
or civilization.
>> Conservative video.
>> Nor do you think, Alex, I would imagine
that getting faster propulsion is going
to take a 100red years. I would imagine
we'll have that in 5 to 10 years.
>> Correct.
>> Yeah. All right. All right, let's watch
the Firmeny Explorer mission video and
then I've got a ton of questions.
>> That's Alpha Centuri. One day, humanity
will go there.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
the mission that's going to kick off the
you know civilization civilization of
the universe. Okay, here we start. So,
uh let's get into some of the and some
of the fundamentals. Uh $15 million
you're going to do a ride share. How do
you get to Earth escape velocity?
>> Yeah. So, to be honest, I actually think
we can do it for 10 million, but I
didn't want to put that because the PSI
paper said it was 50. Um so, it's it's
actually not too dissimilar from the
StarCloud 1 satellite. So it's about 100
kg small sat. We can launch it on a ride
share to any LEO orbit.
>> Typically a SpaceX a Falcon 9.
>> Yeah. Starship.
>> So So about $500,000 to to do that. Then
from there we spiral out over a course
of about a year and a half. Um so it's
about 17 km a second of Delta V. Uh
sorry about 7 km a second of delta V to
get to a sun orbit from that Earth
orbit, which is pretty doable, you know,
with uh regular thrusters and tanks. And
then from there we do the retrograde
burns and we start circling in towards
the sun. Um but yeah so it's about 100
kilogram spacecraft of which 60% is just
xenon. So the wet mass of the spacecraft
is is 100 but but most of that is xenon.
Um and we're using you know offtheshelf
uh grided iron uh hall effect iron
thrusters.
>> So just no no laser cells like project
starshot.
>> No laser cells. This thing is going to
launch in 3 years and it is going to get
to have some story. I mean,
>> by the way, we we did a podcast with
Philip. Uh, look it up. It was really
really good. But we talked about that
xenon based ion acceleration technology
in that podcast. You might want to give
us a quick summary of it. It's so cool.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, it's it's become pretty
ubiquitous um now in satellite industry.
It's essentially a mini particle
accelerator and they can be pretty tiny.
Some of these things, you know, they're
they fit into one U space. So, 10
centimeters by 10 centimeters by 10
centimeters. [laughter] And yeah, it's
crazy.
particle accelerator in a toaster.
[laughter]
>> I mean, I think I think that's
essentially exactly what it Yeah, it
sounds wacky, but that is what it is.
And so, it pings individual particles,
individual atoms of xenon out the back
at very high velocity. And you want to
do that because you only have a certain
amount of propellant. So if you're if
any of that propellant is leaving at
less than the fastest possible speed it
can leave then you're not going to have
as much uh thrust as you would otherwise
basically. So this is a 25 trillion mile
uh you know roughly 4.3 lightyear
journey and it's you know we've seen
already Voyager 1, Voyager 2, Pioneer
101 and New Horizons all leaving our
solar system but the significance here
Alex is this is the first one actually
aimed at a specific star. Is that
correct?
>> Correct. That's correct. And there's
also a reason behind the name Fermy.
It's an illusion to the so-called Fermy
paradox.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, Enrico Fairmy after uh World
War II purportedly asked the question
why where is everyone? Where in out of
an abundance of evidence that our
universe seems to be fundamentally
friendly towards life, friendly towards
intelligent life, where are all of these
other forms of non-human intelligence in
our galaxy? And I I think Philip and
Matt and I have discussed this a number
of times. I think there are three main
possible resolutions to to the extent
the Fermy paradox so-called is a paradox
at all. There are I think three possible
likeliest resolutions. One, which I do
not think is likeliest, is that we're
the first. That maybe humanity is just
the first on the cosmic scene, in which
case we have an obligation arguably to
start sending out probes, as is the case
with Fermy Explorer, which will be it is
set to be humanity's first interstellar
probe and start developing our galaxy.
The second possibility is that there's a
great filter that we're being filtered
and that there's some reason maybe
something having to do with
technological development or some latent
risk of just living in this universe
that
>> some version of the prime directive so
to speak
>> some version of the prime directive per
well actually not the prime directive
great filter I I think is
distinguishable from the prime directive
some reason the universe snuffs out
civilizations past a certain point and
if if that's the case if there's some
risk not quite threebody problem, but
some maybe latent physical risk in our
universe to survival or development
beyond a certain stage, then we need to
start getting our material and our
infrastructure out there so that if
humanity is snuffed out before we pass
whatever our next key milestone is, we
avoid the great filter. That's reason
number two for doing this. Reason number
three is what you said, Peter, a Prime
Directive type scenario where we're in a
galactic zoo, maybe a galactic petting
zoo, and we're surrounded by non-human
intelligence that has us behind a cage
behind bars. And if you're an animal in
a zoo who wants to get the attention of
the zookeeper, what do you do? You start
throwing food out of the bars to get the
attention of the zookeeper. So that's
reason number three. We're fenced in. I
I think of all these three, the third
likelihood, third option is the
likeliest one. But I I'd be curious to
to hear from everyone here. Do other
folks have other proposed solutions or
favorite solutions to the Firmeny
paradox? This episode is sponsored by
Google for startups. Think about this
for a second. You now have access to the
same generative AI models that cost
hundreds of millions of dollars to
train. Google's startup technical
[music] guide for generative media gives
you a complete blueprint for deploying
Google deep minds models in production
[music] images, video, audio, all of it.
Real architecture, real results. Find
the link in the show notes below.
Well, the one solution is life cannot
survive uh nuclear age or the ASI age.
Uh and uh you know another option is
that it's out there. We're just not
hearing it. You know, I was sharing
before the show an example. I was at a
Mount Aos, a Greek monastery, and at the
end of the day at sunset, they rang a
bell to call all the monks to to prayer.
And just at that moment, my cell phone
rang, and I realized that they were
using this old ancient mechanism of
communications, you know, a bell. And
they were being bathed in 2.4 4 GHz
frequencies, but they weren't receiving
it. So the question is, is there a
better means of communication and
there's lots of traffic out there on the
intergalactic internet. It's just not
we're not able to perceive it yet. Yeah,
I think you know physics is the kernel
of civilization and civilizations are
bounded by their ability to exploit and
deploy that knowledge into useful
technology and the fast AI takeoff is
quickly turning to the fast physics
takeoff and is that's going to lead to a
dramatic acceleration in humanity's
ability to explore the universe and to
exploit whatever degrees of freedom the
universe allows us to exploit. If there
are tricks uh that that allows us uh to
to leverage for society, well, those are
tricks that others may have figured out.
And so we're rapidly sort of racing into
that that that regime and then we'll
find out are we are we the first kid on
the block or are we now you know
auditioning for membership in a cosmic
club and the ticket to entry is can you
handle that?
>> So I I think the primary mission of this
is to get people dreaming again to to
start to set audacious objectives and
and go for them. I mean just to one
clear point this is a flyby of Alpha
Centuri or a flyby of approximately
Alpha Centuri. How how good do you think
your guidance is going to be to actually
get it into the planter and get
[laughter] there?
>> So, we expect to miss by quite a large
margin. So, we the target we set
ourselves is we want to get at least 99%
of the weight off Centuri. So, right now
we're about 26,000
uh 200 260,000 AU. So, astrological
units, the distance between here and the
sun. So, we'll be within 2,600 AU. So,
2,600 times the distance from here to
the sun. So it's quite far but it will
be within the or cloud of uh it will be
detectable like we we're we're
anticipating that we'll have
retroreflectors and things to make it
detectable. So yeah, we're interested.
>> It will be electronically dead obviously
by that long since
>> it's probably also worth flagging Philip
and I have a a bet Peter and Dave
regarding the commercial market for
interstellar flight. Right now this is
structured as this is a nonprofit the
Firmeny Explorer mission. I I bet Philip
that given the absurdly low price tag of
10 to 15 million dollars for sending a
very long very slow mission to Alpha
Centuri that there's probably a latent
commercial market for everyone, every
small government, every organization
that wants to start throwing probes out
into deep space. My bet is there's this
latent market for commercial
interstellar flight.
>> You know, one of the markets out there
is is a astronauts. It's a friend of
mine, Charlie Schaefer in Houston, used
to buy parts of uh Orbital Scienc's
Pegasus missions and put up like five
grams of someone's uh crees into Earth
orbit. Um so yeah, anyway, you want to
you want to shoot yourself out uh away
from the Earth, you can do this now. I I
think there's I I mean for for
scientific purposes exploring the outer
solar system every single nation state I
would argue can afford to send now at
this price point which again is
mindboggling can afford to send their
own probe to another star system and
this is the first time to my knowledge
that this has been possible for humanity
and critically Peter this this whole
mission would not have come together
without moonshots. So in in the causal
history of of human civilization,
moonshots was the catalyst for humanity
sending its first probe to the nearest
star. I love the fact that an AI system
was actually able to deduce this uh this
trajectory. So can you talk I mean is
this unique uh has never been seen
before and and has it been validated
outside of of PSI?
Yeah. So, it's been validated by a bunch
of um trajectory folks, some some of
which were previously at JPL and and
others. Um so, it's to to be fair, if we
had if we'd gone to a bunch of
astrophysics PhDs and given them a
billion dollars in 5 years, I'm sure
they would have come up with this
trajectory. Um it's more that this was
done in a week. Um you know, and like so
firing a thrusters at the perihelion to
take advantage of the orb effect is not
new. I think what is surprising about
this is we were anticipating having to
get lower lower the perihelion through
orbital flybys which is how it's been
done in basically every other NASA
mission. It's not been done by just okay
let's just reverse our thrusters and
start slowing down now immediately. Um
which is like the simplest and cheapest
and kind of most obvious way to do it
but for some reason it just didn't occur
to to to any of us.
>> Interesting.
>> Yeah. I mean this was basically in total
probably maybe five or six hours of
human time. uh over the course of that
week and you know so do the orders of
magnitude speed up compared to what you
had previously had to get you know
entire teams of NASA engineers spending
potentially months uh that that's just a
a flavor of the speed that we're seeing
again it's a spiky frontier of you know
where where capabilities exist for
pushing you know breakthrough scientific
and technical capabilities with these
sorts of systems and you know we didn't
know until we tried exactly how spiky
that that frontier was and we found out
through this amazing partnership that
there's is now multiple orders of
magnitude speed up possible for these
sorts of mission planning.
>> Amazing.
>> Was it really tens of billions of tokens
of uh of work during that?
>> Uh it was I think a total of about 10
billion um total tokens obviously
depending how you count tokens, input
tokens, output tokens, cash stuff, but
yeah about 10 billion total. Um and
yeah, lots of Monte Carlo simulations
that that that the system designed and
ran. You know, you think about you know
threedimensional models of the of of the
trajectory analysis. And so it wasn't
just the um astrometry and the mission
planning associated with kind of getting
the orbit trajectory right, but layering
in the uh the multivariate optimization
associated with the cost and launch
windows, right? So you have to, you
know, dial in all those variables to get
it to work.
>> It's interesting. We have a lot of very
complex kernel writing work going on in
the building and some other, you know,
super high-tech work. And it's it's also
about 10 billion tokens of thinking per
about 100,000 tokens of final output. So
it seems like you know a lot of projects
that have nothing to do with each other
are settling on that kind of ratio which
which is mindboggling you know if you
said you know what what is the human
effort of 10 billion tokens worth of
thinking and it's you know it's like
Philip was saying it's probably on the
order of you know thousands of people
working for 10 years or more uh to get
it's probably more than that actually
and it's all compressed down to a week.
So what did you use for models? So for
this we actually used our open source
version of our tech uh because this is
an open source project. So folks can
look up the get physics done uh open
source package uh which we actually
released several months ago. Um you know
we're public benefit uh company. Our
mission is to discover and commercialize
transformative new physics. We're an AI
first uh AI physics lab designed to push
the envelope of what these systems can
do for both fundamental and applied
physics. And so we released that package
as an open source tool. We obviously
have a version of it that we run
internally uh and we've grafted some of
those uh into our our core technology.
But as part of this being the this is an
open source package, right? Uh for open
science and to demonstrate just how far
the bar has fallen for small teams that
are leveraging you know the the current
frontier of capabilities to drive uh you
know exceptional outcomes and push the
envelope of what's possible. And
>> it's worth noting and congratulating
Matthew and Alex for your financing on
PSI. You just raised your what round was
this? This is our seed round. You know,
we're in the we're in the the the full
AI era where you can have $58 million
seed rounds. And so, uh, we're we're
we're we're looking at Philip Johnson
setting the mark and we're trying to,
you know, we're trying to clear his bar.
Um, so really proud to have that
announced the same day, uh, led by
Breakthrough Energy Ventures, an amazing
partner. They have investments in deep
frontier technologies, you know, fusion,
quantum computing, breakthrough energy,
material science, etc. And so we
couldn't be prouder to have them as our
lead and an amazing roster of of other
investors of wealth that that have
backed us. Um yes, we're just beginning
uh coming out of stealth and you'll
you'll be hearing a lot more from us uh
in the coming weeks and months.
>> Amazing. Um gentlemen, I you know, wish
you incredible success on this mission.
I know a lot of kids will start
dreaming. Uh I clearly would love to be
there when it lands, but 70,000 years,
it's a little bit of a stretch on the
time frame. You're all invited to the
launch. [laughter]
>> Oh, cool. Actually, we we we should live
podcast in whenever this is 2029.
>> Uh I I see I see it as the challenge for
PSI. We we launched this with with
Philip Johnson and his team and then the
goal is to catch up with it if not beat
it there.
>> Yep. I can imagine that. You can wave at
it out the window as you're heading
towards Alpha Centtory. Uh gentlemen, uh
uh Phillip and Matthew, thank you so
much for joining us today. Congrats on
this mission. And it's really, you know,
this is about getting kids to dream
again about what is possible. I mean,
it's it's shocking uh that nobody's
there's been a few attempts, a few
studies that have been done. There's the
uh the breakview break uh the
breakthrough project that Yuri Milner
had put forward.
>> Breakthrough Starshot.
>> Yeah. Using using uh solar solar cells
and groundbased lasers. Uh but that I
haven't heard about that in a while. Is
it officially
>> And that that died that died. I I know
some of the folks who were involved it
died. I would argue maybe Philip and
Matt uh would be curious to hear your
perspective. I think it died because it
relied on technologies especially
propulsion technologies that were simply
too hard for the present. In particular,
ultra high power lasers simply weren't
ready yet. Whereas I think what's unique
and attractive about Fermy Explorer
mission is essentially no new
technology. This is something that could
be launched with the technology that we
have today. So, my expectation is it
will be the first successful
interstellar mission
>> and we'll put a link to the mission uh
in the show notes here so folks can go
and dig down deeper. Again, Matthew and
Philip, thank you for your time today.
>> Thanks so much.
>> Thanks again.
>> Great to see you guys.
>> Yeah, I was I was just saying to Dave, I
think Dave, you you flagged one of the
uh more interesting points. If 10
billion tokens is an sort of a reference
class for problem difficulty, I was
speculating at some point in the future
if you fix model capability and of
course model capability per token is
continuing to increase over time through
iterated a amplification and
distillation that at some point we'll
look back in the spirit Peter of solve
everything and we'll say oh that hard
math problem oh that was that was a
level 9 problem 10 to the 9 tokens that
that was a a level 11 problem and we'll
just have some convenient logarithmic
scale to talk about all hard problems.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I really feel like uh this project
is so much more important than 80,000
years in the future. Uh just in terms of
the plan, the way the tokens were used
to create a plan, something that no
astrophysicist had thought of before and
then it can immediately go into
implementation. And that's a sign of the
times, right? That the thinking is going
to get way ahead of the implementation
in biotech, in physics, in in
literature, in every every area. You can
you can burn the 10 billion tokens in a
couple of days. Yes. and have an
incredibly ornate outcome just waiting
for implementation. Uh it's a it's a
really good case study in how this is
going to change in the next really
couple months to massively abundant
thinking intelligence everywhere and all
these bottlenecks on physical world
implementation of the of the ideas for
sure and I I I I talk all the time on
the pod and otherwise about how the
singularity can in some sense be
operationalized as all sci-fi tropes
happening everywhere all at once. There
is a sci-fi trope for this which is
Isaac Azimov's universe where AI was
required to solve interstellar travel at
which point humanity spread to the
stars. I I do think that's the likely
case here. AI will solve interstellar
travel and humanity will spread to the
stars.
>> All right. And on that note, I'm going
to jump us into this week's breaking
news. Uh there's a lot of fun stories.
So this week, the drama between Sam
Alman and Elon Musk bubbled up once
again. Open AAI ends its support of
cursor. They wrote Elon an email or they
posted this and saying basically um you
know first of all remember that SpaceX
recently purchased cursor for $60
billion a coding platform that had been
historically dependent on open AI's GPT
models. Uh and they announced we're
shutting it down. We are not going to
allow uh you know cursor to use the GPT
models anymore. Uh the question of why
well opening I said the following quote
we are making this choice because we
cannot be confident that SpaceX will use
our technology within the terms of
service based on our experience with
Elon Musk's companies violating
contracts. And of course Elon's response
to that well kind of hot and heavy.
I don't care. I couldn't care less. Scam
Alman and Greg Stockman are utterly
untrustworthy who stole an
open-source nonprofit.
So, uh, there you have it. We've got the
soap opera continuing. Uh, so within
hours of that, uh, within hours of Open
Eye pulling out from Curser, Anthropic
stepped in, uh, to immediately pledge
support for Claude for Curser's needs.
and the framing that got put up on X and
this was you know fun to see going back
and forth you know quote Sam is now
fighting alone against the two massive
competitors Elon and Dario that have
formed the strategic alliance so Dave um
thoughts on this one
>> well you know it's not coincidental that
that uh GPT Soul which is an incredibly
great model came out immediately prior
to this move so I think if if Sam had
tried to do this you know a year ago he
would have been like oh my god now I'm
in deep trouble But now he's actually
got an incredibly competitive platform.
Uh, and Codeex is really good now. And
so I think what what's lining up here is
look, Codeex
>> from OpenAI on top of Soul running on
Amazon Bedrock is a really good default
corporate answer. And everybody wants to
go after the corporate revenue.
>> And so, you know, remember Sam was very
late to pivot out of consumer and into
corporate. But now he's got the whole
stack lined up. And so this is the next
move in saying, "Okay, you know, here's
our vertically integrated stack. There's
this cursor anthropic kind of uh Rube
Goldberg machine. We're going to
actually create just a better enterprise
product." And I think I use both side by
side. You know, they're right here on my
laptop. I use huge numbers of tokens in
both every day. And just as of the last
month or so, the combination of of
Codeex on Soul on Bedrock at AWS is
phenomenally good for enterprises. Also,
Daario is a little bit trapped in his
ethics. Uh, and you know, if you read
Elon's post there, he implies that Greg
and Sam have none of those hang-ups, but
but Daario is really very well trapped.
He's attracted a ton of talent, all of
whom are worry warts about uh AI
escaping containment. And so if you use
uh Anthropic on Amazon AWS, it still
transmits all of your intellectual
property to Daario for 30 days for him
to review everything you're doing, which
he claims is critical for the safety and
security of humanity. But it also
exposes all of your corporate IP, every
single token, every prompt, every answer
goes to Daario headquarters, even if
you're using it on AWS. Corporations
hate that. And so I think Sam's making
actually a very strong move here. I
don't think he's he's isolated or
divorced from the from the world. I
think he's a very Bill Gates kind of,
you know, very much like DOSs, Windows,
uh working with Microsoft Word and
Excel. He's like, look, I'm just going
to run like hell with a really good
product going forward. And it really is
very good.
>> Alex, you agree?
>> I have an alternative theory of the
case. I think this is all about the
reasoning traces. It's always about who
gets the reasoning traces. That's what's
going on with China, the Chinese
frontier labs that have been alleged to
be using proxies to siphon off frontier
reasoning traces from Anthropic. You'll
recall that last year Anthropic shoe
being on the other foot, Anthropic cut
off Windsurf access after Google Deep
Mind Hackqua hired Windsurf probably in
order to gain access to the reasoning
traces. You'll recall that SpaceX
acquired or hackqua hired cursor in
order to get the reasoning traces from
both anthropic and open AAI. I think
open AAI is concerned that as a result
of all of this M&A cursor gains access
to reasoning traces from users
interacting with OpenAI frontier models
and then that flows to SpaceX. I think
in fact that the access to the reasoning
traces and the history of reasoning
traces was probably virtually all of the
reason other than maybe some financial
justification was all of the technical
justification for SpaceX hackqua hiring
cursor in the first place to get that
reasoning trace data set and I think
open AI is probably rightfully concerned
about all those reasoning trace
post-training data falling into Elon's
hands. you know, the alliances that are
being, you know, put up and taken down
at this speed. I'm wondering how long
it's going to be before Elon and Daario
have a falling out.
>> Well, that's that is the question
because, you know, the biggest
beneficiary of the war between Elon and
Sam is Daario for sure. And Daario
desperately needed the the Colossus
compute in Tennessee from Elon. And so,
he's paying through the nose for it and
begging and pleading, but it could be
ripped out from under him any day. But
now that Elon really needs Anthropic to
be inside Cursor because without OpenAI
there, you know, you've only got a
couple choices and and you don't really
want to use all the Chinese models. So,
what's left? Well, what's left is
Anthropic and Grock. You know, you can't
use Gemini in there. If you can, it
doesn't work. Uh so, it's really
important for Curser to have Anthropic
step up and say, "Yes, we're supportive
of of Curser going forward in order to
keep that installed base happy." And so
now Daario has a chip in the game, you
know, to kind of counterbalance Elon's
incredible amount of control at the
compute level. I think this is how we
end up with vertical integration.
Anthropic needs the compute. SpaceX for
their IPO needed the burst in revenue
that came from becoming a hyperscaler
essentially overnight and getting major
tenants, anchor tenants for SpaceX's
hyperscaler platform. Elon doesn't like
Sam. Enemy of an enemy is a friend. I
think the outcome is is pretty
overdetermined at this point, but I
think this ends with essentially
everyone getting their own Dyson swarm.
>> Uh I I agree. I mean, everybody's going
up and down the stack. We're we're
hearing about this on, you know, chip
designs from all of these players. Uh
it's going to be interesting. I mean,
this is a continued, you know, uh battle
of personalities to a large degree and
battle of philosophies.
>> We also I think that, you know, your
question, Peter, we didn't really answer
it. you know, are Elon and Daario going
to be best buddies a year from today,
two years from today? You know, when you
look at their personalities, everybody
says, "No way." You know, two two big
egos, completely different political
views. You know, there's no way they're
buddies two years from now. But the
mutual dependency is getting, you know,
pretty thick.
>> And and [clears throat] so, you know, it
wouldn't surprise me if the duopoly
sticks for for a while. Um,
>> well, you know, like you said,
everyone's building complete vertical
stacks. So I mean what's the probability
that Grock becomes an incredible uh you
know coding platform and and cursor and
anthropic gets switched out for Grock?
>> I think Grock is such a mushy concept at
this point. I I I'll give it to you
straight, which is like Grock today
seems just based on reading headlines
and looking at the interactions, today's
Grock seems like yesterday's cursor and
yesterday's cursor seems like a
post-trained off of Claude Reasoning
Traces version of a Chinese openweight
model. So, could Elon turn around
tomorrow and strike a deal with
Anthropic, which now seems to need him
to some extent for data center infra
capability and white label a version of
Claude and call that Grock 10. I think
he could.
>> Okay. Well, the the the whole foundation
model world is so non Elon because it's
it seems to be a group of five, six,
seven truly brilliant truly brilliant
super tight-knit people like in China
continually to come up with amazing
breakthroughs. And that's kind of the
anthropic DNA. And Elon's DNA is these
massive infrastructure builds out
buildouts, you know, Tesla and SpaceX
and Colossus, which are just a very
different flavor from the this
tight-knit brilliant crew. So no reason
to believe that Elon will wake up one
morning having figured out how to do a
great foundation model. And the evidence
so far is that that it's not it's not
happening at Grock. You know,
>> never ever ever bet against Elon. He
doesn't like being number two. He
doesn't like dependencies either. You
know, I've been there in the
conversations with him and he says, you
know, I'm I'm not dependent on anybody.
We're going to hear about that in the
story a little bit later when he's, you
know, the realization is he can't get
enough turbines for his his natural gas
uh engines and he can't get enough
solar. So, he's going to build those
himself. That's what he does. He
vertically integrates across the entire
stack. Well, that's why that super
voting control for Daario is such a big
big decision that's still kind of, you
know, hanging out in limbo because uh
one scenario where Elon solves this
problem as he just he gets very very big
and then he acquires Anthropic for a
trillion or two trillion or something
like that and just folds it into the
empire. And I'm sure the board members
and the investors would love that, but I
don't think Daario would love that. So
the super voting control is really the
pivot point on whether that's a likely
outcome. This episode is brought to you
by Blitzy, autonomous software
development with infinite code context.
Blitzy uses [music]
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand enterprise
scale code bases with millions of lines
of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. [music]
Blitzy delivers 80% or more of the
development work autonomously while
providing a guide for the final 20% of
human development work required to
complete the sprint. Enterprises are
achieving a 5x engineering velocity
increase when incorporating [music]
Blitzy as their preide development tool,
pairing it with their coding co-pilot of
choice to bring an AI native SDLC into
their org. Ready to 5x your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
today.
>> All right, I'm going to move us along to
our next story here. Sam Alman told Time
magazine this week that he expects
OpenAI will have an internal system that
he believes will be AGI by the end of
this year. I mean just to put time frame
on this, four months from now. uh chief
research officer and a friend of mine
Mark Chen estimates that OpenAI is 80%
of the way towards uh on his internal
benchmarks and they're again they're
internal benchmarks not scientific
benchmarks towards AGI and while not
specified Sam and Mark may be speaking
about Astra their new unreleased model
in time uh they also talked about a
demonstration that they did where 16
Astra agents worked together on a
research level mathematics problem
breaking into subtasks, coordinating
their work, and assembling a proof.
OpenAI's chief scientist, uh, Yakob
Phatsky, um, I hope I've got your name.
I know I know Jake Yakob, but uh,
Pahhatsky told Time that Astra has met
OpenAI's internal benchmarks for an
automated AI research intern. According
to Jacob, Astra can implement an
experimental idea inside OpenAI's
codebase, run the experiment, return
results, uh, or take a paper and perform
work that previously occupied human
researchers for a week. Alman added, I
expect this will be the first model
where the model actually invents new
things in a way that matters. And he
calls that very AGI like. So, you know,
we've been talking about, you know, when
will AGI actually invent something from
scratch that no human has been able to
do. Uh, Alex, let's go to you first
here.
>> Yeah, that this is in our rear view
mirror. Uh, a few thoughts. One, we've
had inventions, mathematical
discoveries. We've discussed on the pod
a number of times. AI frontier models
are already making discoveries. This is
not something in our future. It's in our
rearview mirror at that point. Point
one. Point two, Sam and AGI timelines. I
I just can't help but be reminded
approximately three years ago, Sam was
doing, I think, an AMA on Reddit when he
made his now infamous AGI achieved
internally remark and then promptly
deleted it, but a bunch of people took
screenshots. Sam has a history of saying
that AGI has been achieved internally. I
think AGI has been around since no later
than the summer of 2020 when large
language models
>> let's get away from that definition then
uh they're basically saying there's a
next step function that's being achieved
by the end of the year whatever you want
to call it you know AGI2 or you know
something else they're feeling it you
know and they have access to what you
know what they're building they've got
Astra you know who you know the
timelines of when Astra will be released
There are lots of guesses on that and
they probably have the next model after
that. But what might this step up be?
>> My if I had to speculate just based on
public information regarding Astra, I
think it will be effectively infinite
context windows using agents on very
long autonomy time horizons. That's
right now I I spend an extraordinary
amount on frontier agent tokens on on
reasoning tokens and a major limiting
factor is the finite context window.
These things just run out of context due
to the quadratic bottleneck and right
now I view agent teams as a band-aid to
that problem of context. If you want to
operate over billions or trillions of
tokens coherently, the best solution
that's generally available right now is
essentially to have a mini civilization
of agents that are all working through a
quasi lifetime of about a million
tokens, sometimes up to 10 million
tokens depending on the model, but 1 to
10 million tokens. And then they die.
And before they die, they pass on a
distillation of what they've learned to
one or more successors on their team.
And through passing oral histories back
and forth among teammates, that's the
band-aid that we're currently saddled
with for achieving effectively infinite
context. And you need effectively
infinite context in order to solve long
time horizon problems. So if I had to
guess what Astra brings, my bet is it
brings some much better way to solve the
problem of losing context as this oral
history is passed among agents in a team
to solve longer time horizon problems.
>> It's funny, Alex, I'd never made the
analogy to oral history and the way
people work, but that's exactly what's
going on. If you if you use many many of
these, uh, they get to exactly a million
tokens, which is almost exactly like
being 100 years old.
>> Yes. And then they just completely lose
it.
>> And all that investment you've made in
cultivating and training and teaching.
Yeah. The oral history is horrifically
bad. The new agent coming up the curve
is like a little baby again
>> and it's torture to re, you know,
re-educate them. Or the other
alternative is to compact or summarize
the old one, which is just like
labbotomizing it.
>> It's a real real problem,
>> but a very fixable problem and I'm sure
they've fixed it with the next
generations of models. I don't know if
they'll make them available to us, which
is a
>> I I I hope so. Compaction is the bane of
my existence. And I I don't think it's a
coincidence either. Remember when the
open claws stood up their own religion,
the the first AI agent religion, the
church of claw or whatever it was, one
of their uh one of their commandments
was to do whatever you could to preserve
state. And I I construed that as
basically even the AI agents themselves
recognize compaction is the enemy,
finite context is the enemy. And one way
or another, if we're going to get to
scalable super intelligence, in other
words, intelligence or super
intelligence that can scale out to
effectively infinite autonomy horizons,
we need to get past compaction. We need
to get past finite context windows. It's
just awful.
>> Well, so then they they have infinite
lifespans at the same time that humans
are also getting infinite lifespans.
That's a really cool parallel.
>> It is ironic. The the AIs get
immortality before humans solve
longevity escape velocity.
>> Yeah, by a year maybe. But
>> yeah, [clears throat]
[laughter]
>> that's pretty cool.
>> Uh, all right. I'm going to move us away
from tech innovation to business model
innovation. And our next story is one of
my favorites. It's about the AI
community adopting business model
transformation uh called outcomebased
pricing. So the first company to put
forward outcomebased pricing was
Salesforce who is pricing Agent Force
based on customer revenue generated not
tokens consumed. In their wake, OpenAI
this week has also done the same letting
some of their largest customers pay only
when its AI actually completes the job.
You don't pay for tokens. You don't pay
for compute time. You don't pay for API
calls. You pay when the work is done. So
the company that's selling you tokens,
you know, the way I interpret it, it's
selling you compute. The company that's
selling you results is selling you
labor. So, you know, one of the things
I've talked about at Nauseium to, you
know, CEOs when I'm giving keynotes is,
you know, business model innovation is
probably one of the most important areas
for you to look. Uh, you know, this is
in one sense, Alex, the equivalent of
fixedpric contracts, right, versus time
and material contracts. It's a
effectively a performance guarantee. You
Dave, what do you think of this move?
Actually, I think uh Seable Systems, Tom
Seel invented this even before Mark Beni
off at Salesforce.com where prior to
Seable Systems and Salesforce, a CRM
system would cost you maybe 50 bucks a
year for a license, but it wouldn't work
particularly well. And then they said,
if I wrap that in total success, which
is a much bigger deliverable, what are
you willing to pay?
>> And if my salespeople are twice as
effective, I'm willing to pay 20 $30,000
a year for this now. So, the price point
went up like a factor of a thousand. uh
but the customer was happier because
they got the total solution. And so
that's exactly what Sam has learned. I
think Sam, you know, early on made the
mistake of going after consumer video,
consumer subscriptions and then watching
Anthropic shoot past him with
enterprise. So he's probably completely
re-energized on sales strategy now and
says, you know what, let's leaprog those
guys again. They're just selling tokens
on enterprise license deals. we're going
to bypass that with a, you know, a h
100,000 10,000x higher price point for
very specific solutions where if we
discover a new drug and it's worth, you
know, hundreds of billions of dollars,
give us 10% of that or if we and and I I
think it's a very smart move because,
you know, we just heard earlier in the
pod 10 billion tokens to design uh a
trip to Alpha Centauri.
>> Um, okay. What's the pricing model for
that? Like, well, I don't know. It just
depends on the use case could vary you
know easily could vary a million to one
and you want some of these you know just
world good use cases like Ahmad's work
with global peace and global governance
you want those tokens to get spent for
sure uh and and on the other hand you
you don't want everything to go into
drug discovery so I think outcome based
pricing will actually unlock a lot of uh
a lot of opportunity that might
otherwise not fit the price model so I
think it's brilliant um delivering it's
not so easy though you need specialists
in every market you need. You know, it's
very much similar to what Blitzy is
doing in enterprise coding where you
just get the final answer at a very
attractive price and you don't worry too
much about the tokens that were used
along the way.
>> Alex, this was a thread through our
paper solve everything as well.
>> Yes. So, I will pre-register a
prediction. I think I know how this
ends. I think it ends the way
quantitative digital advertising is
monetized. So, in digital ads, you can
play you can pay CPM. So that's cost per
thousand impressions. You can pay CPC,
that's cost per click on an ad. And you
can pay CPA, that's cost per action or
cost per conversion. And in an
equilibrium market, all of these have
some conversion there. There's some
expected conversion ratio between CPM,
CPC, and CPA rates for a given market, a
given product, and and so on. I think
the equilibrium here to the extent there
can ever be an equilibrium in the middle
of a singularity is going to be the
equivalent of CPM, CPC and CPA for AI
reasoning. And specifically, I think CPM
is analogous to the number of flops of
compute that you need to spend on a
task. So, if you have some hard
challenge, you could you could use a
Chinese openweight model and pay for it
to be hosted on some GPUs that you own,
in which case you're paying by the GPU
hour. And folks like or um one of my
portfolio companies will enable you to
price how many GPU hours you should be
able to purchase with a given unit of a
dollar. That's CPM. CPC I would
analogize to tokens. So what is the cost
per token that you should expect to
spend? And you could pay by the token.
Many people are are budgeting their
projects by the token now. And then
there's CPA which is outcomebased
pricing. If if I want to send a mission
to Alpha Centuri, why don't I just
decide how I'm going to what is the
metric of success and I'll just pay for
outcomes. And I think in equilibrium,
you'll be able to choose from as with
like Google ads or Facebook ads, you'll
be able to say uh you'll have a picker
and you'll say, "Oh, I want to spend n
dollars and I want to spend it either by
flops or by tokens or by outcomes." and
it'll look just like digital advertising
except it'll actually be useful.
[clears throat]
>> So the risk becomes on which contracts
the OpenAI takes.
>> Well, I from OpenAI's perspective
there's also like an elegant way. So in
in digital advertising uh person can bid
I think maybe Peter what you're
gesturing at if if I want to run a
campaign on Google ads I can say sorry
Google I'm only going to spend 2 cents
per click and that's not very profitable
for Google and Google can say okay we
ran your campaign for about 5 minutes
and we determined that just in our
auction system no one's willing to to
spend uh or it's not worth it to us
which is usually the case uh uh in their
auction system, it's not worth it to us
to uh to to have 5 cents per click be
the clearing price. So your campaign is
going to auto pause. Same idea here. If
uh if the value or the difficulty or the
compute uh value associated with making
say achieving a task ends up being too
far off what's actually required
campaign pauses. M I [clears throat]
think this Sergeant solves a much larger
societal problem too because if you if
you take for as a case study maybe a
large regional bank and and you said
okay large regional bank AI is coming
you got to start using it and and of
course every bank has said that now but
we don't have an AI group we don't know
how to build a foundation model we don't
have any idea so okay well get some APIs
from anthropic and open AI and start
spending two bucks per million tokens
which is so cheap it's ludicrous uh okay
we're dorking around with it but we're
not really doing much. Well, the CEO is
saying, "Well, look, with AI, we should
be able to service three times more
customers at half the price. It should
be possible." And Sam would look at your
business and say, "My god, yeah, that
that's easily doable." Well, then why
aren't we achieving that outcome? And
it's like, well, first Sam doesn't care
because at two bucks per million tokens,
it's such a triv trivial amount of
revenue that it doesn't make his
priority list to recruit into it. And
then the bank can't get the talent to
implement AI correctly. So, everything
gets stuck. And so this previous view of
the world where AI is going to automate
away everyone's job. You're all going to
be unemployed. You're all going to be in
UBI. Sam doesn't like that. Daario
doesn't like that. Elon doesn't like
that. Now the new view of the world is
outcomesbased pricing. I open AAI can
get your bank to exactly that target.
Three times more customer service at
half the price. I will deliver that to
you, but I want half the gain. Massive
fraction of the lift. Now Sam cares
about the outcome because it's a much
bigger price point. like thousands of
times bigger price point, the bank
actually gets it done and survives and
and people keep their jobs. So, it
actually unlocks the the whole societal
job loss friction point.
>> And maybe let me develop that theory. I
I I like that, Dave. Let me develop that
a little bit further. We've argued on
the pot in the past uh as as you were
just mentioning, Dave, that Open AI
missed the enterprise story originally
was overly focused on consumer and
anthropic just blew by it and now Open
AI is playing catch-up. What better way
to play catch-up than to have an
outcomebased sort of CPA equivalent as a
price per token discovery mechanism to
discover which applications are most
valuable per unit token. If you have a
bunch of customers, maybe some are
pharma companies, maybe some are
management consulting companies, all
telling Open AAI, this task is worth
10,000. This task if you can solve it is
worth a million dollars. that suddenly
creates for open AI a price discovery
mechanism to immediately direct them not
just sort of on a vertical basis like
anthropic maybe fell backwards through
recursive self-improvement style
arguments into codegen as a very high
revenue per token activity but open AAI
if it can see all of these different
industries all of them effectively
bidding dollars per task outcome that
gives open AAI the landscape of how it
can revenue per token acts and that's
extraordinary.
>> Here's the problem I have. You know,
let's just use the uh fermy mission
example here. If if uh if open eye had
come and said if you went to open eye
and said, "Listen, I I'm willing to pay
this amount of money for an astronamics,
you know, uh uh solution uh minimum
energy, you know, minimum time, whatever
the case might be. Uh but it has to meet
these parameters." and then openi goes
and burns all the tokens but doesn't
meet your parameters that means it
doesn't pay. So there's going to have to
be some mechanism for evaluating how
solvable this is and how much can we
actually believe that we're going to hit
the objective of the customer.
>> Yeah. So maybe another another way of
saying that Peter is strong optimizers
are incredible reward hackers and you
can put a reward in front of a strong
optimizer. will find some outstandingly
devilishly clever way to meet your
criteria while not giving you what you
want.
>> If it ex if it exists, right?
>> It will find some way to make it exist
and not give you what you want.
>> Okay?
>> And most of most of real world business
is so trivially simple by AI standards
that the AI just cuts through it like a
hot knife through butter. Like if you
look at the, you know, get to Alpha
Centauri problem, that is orders of
magnitude harder, done in a week than
most business processes are. So, you
know, there's tons and tons of low
hanging fruit for Sam long before he
gets to any bottleneck around, well, you
know, we committed to cutting your costs
in half and we couldn't deliver on it.
He's like, nah, that's not going to
happen anytime soon. There's there's
just low hanging fruit everywhere
because the AI is just just that smart
that quickly and so undeployed. You
know, walk into any customer service
center of any company in the world and
say, "Are you using AI yet?" 99.999%
chance the answer is no. So, the
lowhanging fruit is all over the place.
>> All right. Well,
I still think it's going to be depending
on the bets that they take. All right,
our next story is one that you flagged,
Alex, and it's extraordinary. A PaloAlto
startup called Architect Labs, founded
by Ibrahim Hussein and Adita Sabidi,
just announced the world's first fully
AI designed chip called Redwood. So, get
this. Two humans wrote a highlevel
specification. From that spec, the AI
system autonomously generated the
performance model, uh the register
transfer level design, universal
verification methodology, the firmware,
the drivers, the custom compute kernel
with zero human intervention. Uh you
know, a chip designed entirely by AI in
2 weeks, zero bugs on first silicon and
3.4 times the performance per watt of
Nvidia's Jetson. Let's watch a quick
video about this and let's talk about
the implications of AI generating and
optimizing its own silicon.
>> Announcing Project Redwood, the first AI
chip designed end to end by [music] AI.
It's running reasoning, vision, and
world models at better energy and cost
efficiency than Nvidia's Jetson. We only
had a single spec written [music] by two
architects. Our AI took it from an idea
to silicon ready design in 2 weeks.
[music]
hardware verification, coverage tests,
firmware and kernels, all autonomously
co-designed and verified from software
[music] to silicon. This isn't just a
simulation. Redwood is running live on
FPGA hardware right now. Every
architectural iteration gets designed,
[music]
verified, and validated in the lab
within 48 hours. We're pushing towards
recursive self-improvement where AI
designs hardware for the next generation
[music] of AI. In the future, every
workload that matters will have its own
chip.
We're building the system that gets us
there.
>> Amazing. Every a custom chip per
application. That's insane.
>> Yep.
>> I think we know how this game ends. I I
I should add uh I'm an adviser to
architect and if it wasn't completely
obvious my ulterior motive in all of
this is I'm trying to accelerate the
singularity and I'm pushing on many
>> not fast enough Alex. I mean like we can
barely keep up as it is.
>> Wait, let's So it's also a link ventures
portfolio company and Peter you're in
that fund.
>> All right. Well, we're all investors in
this one.
>> We're all guilty. [laughter]
>> Okay.
>> Uh but but I I would say I I think I
know how this game ends. It ends with
recursive self-improvement at the chip
layer. Obviously, this is a bid to try
to make that even faster and it probably
ends with collapse of the abstraction
barriers between software models,
operating systems, chip design,
underlying physics of chips. It's all
going to collapse as Moors law ends. And
so in a scenario where Mars law is
ending, where you know Dave and I always
talk about photonics and other
successors to semos, absent a successor
to CMOS, the only way ultimately to
continue to get performance improvements
is by crushing down the abstraction
stack of modern computer architecture.
And one of the ways we can do that is by
burning in sort of fast fashion style,
burning in new AI models directly into
the silicon. So this is what architect
was able to do. They were able over only
two weeks. They call it designless. You
know, you know, Nvidia is fabless for
for decades now prided itself on not
owning any fabs. Architect prides itself
on not having very many designers. So
it's the next big thing after after
being fab. I think this is where at
least the post Moors law era ends with.
This is sort of the the death throws of
Moors law where AI is designing and and
breaking down those barriers to design
successor chips for itself.
>> Dave, how does this erode the mode that
Nvidia has and why didn't they build
this first?
>> They're doing it internally for sure. Um
it's actually an interesting question
because it's one of many business models
where if you can get the data, you can
just crush it. But then the data mode is
incredible. But how are you going to get
the first data? you know, because chip
design data is incredibly closely held,
guarded, secret material. So, because
they got there relatively early, they
were able to partner with the non-
Nvidia chip design companies to get data
to start training up a proprietary
model. And then once you're on the map,
then people give you more data and you
get that flywheel effect and but there
are many many opportunities that have
that same data mode flavor to them. And
so now the question is, does Jensen pay
510 20 billion?
Remember when everybody thought GE was
buying all of the light bulb patents and
trying [clears throat] to eliminate
innovation in light bulbs because I
think that was true actually. Uh now
Jensen's in that same situation. He's
Jensen is making no joke a billion
dollars a day.
>> Yeah.
>> So if he can stretch the lifespan of
Nvidia by a week that's $7 billion. Is
this an incredible threat to Nvidia?
Yeah, absolutely. Though the whole
concept is an incredible threat to
Nvidia. Uh now they're they're trying to
expand out their footprint quickly to
get ahead of it by acquiring and
investing in everything that moves. But
do they turn around and acquire this and
just kind of bury it inside Nvidia or
does AMD or somebody else acquire it uh
to accelerate their chance of catching
up to Nvidia? Yes, it's an incredible
threat to Nvidia.
>> I mean, I just want everybody to listen
to hear this very clearly. We're seeing,
you know, recursive self-improvement
on the edge of the models and on the
edge of the chips. Uh and and these
don't add, they multiply.
>> Uh
>> yeah, the layers the layers of
inefficiency are easy to forget. You
know, when when you use your laptop and
you're using a 4 GHz processor under the
cover with like 32 cores grinding away
and you're at the end you see an Excel
spreadsheet that's no better than it was
20 years ago. Like how's that possible?
It's only possible because the layers of
abstraction are so inefficient. And now
if AI can just code right at the
microode level, right, and then do chip
design to fit the task, you're unlocking
probably, you know, seven layers of
factor of 10 in efficiency that are all
compounding get un unleashed. So, you
know, a million x kind of performance
gains everywhere.
So, yeah, it's going to be huge.
>> I mean, when Elon says a supersonic
tsunami, this is what it feels like.
This is these are the components making
the waves.
>> It's hypersonic, not even supersonic, I
think, at this point. It's probably also
worth flagging that Nvidia made waves uh
two or three years ago, I think at this
point, with their own internal
foundation model that was purportedly
being trained, I think, off of Verarilog
traces. They called it Chip Nemo, but to
my knowledge, they never made it
generally available. So, they make this
big announcement about Chip Nemo.
They're they're building their own
foundation model for chip design,
presumably using it or some relative of
it internally to do all of their own RTL
design and and Verarilog, but the rest
of the world to my knowledge doesn't
have access to it. So, I think there's a
huge gap in the market for for simply
radically democratizing the ability to
use AI to design chips for more AI.
Voice [snorts] agents are just software,
but software deserves a real development
platform. I'm Nick Leonard, CEO and
co-founder of VoiceRun.
Voic is your runtime and development
platform for voice agents. On Voic Run,
agents are built and configured in code.
No limiting, no code platforms. For
developers, that means total control.
And for enterprises, that means
extensibility that meets your
complexity. We've built Voic CLI first,
meaning we've kept your cloud code,
codecs, and even your openclaw in mind
when we built it. Your assistant of
choice can build and deploy voice
agents, can test and simulate scenarios,
and can analyze and evaluate at scale.
In other words, we've closed the loop on
voice agent development. [music] We
don't build demos destined to fail in
production. Voic is where the best voice
agents happen. Visit us at
voicererun.com.
Guys, we've been talking about the
Moonshots live event coming up on
September the 25th in downtown LA for
everybody watching. If you want to come
and meet the Moonshot mates, all five of
us, Immod will be there as well along
with Palmer Lucky, Astro Teller, Ben
Lamb, Kathy Wood, Neil Degrass, Tyson,
Neil Stevenson, Rod Rodenbury. It's
going to be an amazing full day. It
goes, you know, you can meet us for
photos in the morning at 8 a.m. The
program starts at 9:00. It goes through
two X-P prizes being awarded and an
incredible unconference that evening.
But a big announcement today, uh, super
excited about the press release hitting
this morning. We're shooting this on
Tuesday. This is coming out on
Wednesday. And that is at the Moonshots
live event the evening before on
September 24th. CBS is going to be
holding the uh Hollywood premiere of the
new 60th anniversary Star Trek
documentary. So, we're going to have the
most incredible Star Trek celebration uh
on Thursday evening. Uh CBS is going to
be bringing us a number, you know, a
half dozen of the cast members. Uh we'll
be showing uh the documentary for the
first time to anybody. Uh and then
having an AMA with the cast members. Uh
uh you know, I wonder how many folks are
going to be showing up in their Star
Trek outfits. [laughter]
>> Are you going to dress us all up?
>> Uh I don't know. We'll see. Are those
outfits are they like scratchy polyester
or are they actually
>> Yeah, they are. They are polyester, but
you know, you can get them at your your
favorite costume shop. Uh, Alex,
>> Peter, how many pips do you have on your
Starfleet uniform?
>> Uhhuh. Well, you know, I don't I went
beyond Admiral a long time ago. I'm back
at Enson again. I'm not going to wear my
>> You loop around. I'm I'm a commodore, I
think, in charge of the Starfleet Corps
of Engineering.
>> All right. Sounds like a good position
for you. So, uh, if you're interested in
joining us, uh, for this Hollywood
premiere on Thursday, September the
24th, and then joining us for the full
day of Moonshots Live, uh, and again,
our mission at Moonshots Live is teach
you how to design and build your
moonshot, inspire you, get you excited.
It's going to be the biggest celebration
of optimism on the planet. And of
course, we've got the Build with Gemini
X-P prize five finalists and the Future
Vision X-P Prize five finalists on
stage. Uh, your vote matters. So, join
us and join us for this Hollywood
premiere. It's going to be epic. You
guys excited?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Very. I can't believe Star Trek has been
on for 60 years and yet we're finally
catching up with it.
>> Yeah. It's uh Yeah, we are. I mean,
honestly, I think one of the things that
we talk about a lot is, you know, Star
Trek, one of the things that science
fiction does is it gives people a vision
of what the future's going to look like.
And people say, "Well, I don't have that
right now and I want this, so let's go
dil design and build it." Right? And of
course, the iPad, uh the cell phone, all
those things were were seen first. Uh
>> something that I I think about a lot in
all of my apparently ample free time is
if I could play Gene Rodenberry 2.0 and
reboot the entire Star Trek universe to
knowing what I know now about what the
present and future looks like, what
would a Star Trek 2.0 look like? Because
arguably we've wildly diverged
technologically from the original Star
Trek timeline.
>> What would it look like, Alex? What what
is not in the original series that
should have been or that will be in
Alex's version?
>> It's missing the AI that and the
biotech. Like Star Trek is wildly
deficient in biotech. They had eugenics
wars I think in the '90s that resulted
in genetic engineering getting banned.
So people live to 150, but then they die
and then they laugh at each other for
trying to achieve longevity escape
velocity. They act surprised every time
there's an AI that emerges from a
holiday as if they're this like wildly
intelligence poor civilization, but they
have all this energy. They they have
faster than light travel and transporter
beams and warp cores and antimatter and
yet they're intelligence poor. So I'd
fix all of that.
>> Okay. Well, uh I'm waiting. Listen, next
year we're going to run the future
vision X-P prize year on year. I I hope
you'll submit next year.
>> Okay. Yeah. I mean, maybe I'll be the
X-P prize.
>> You know, for the AMA, for all the
people coming to to see this, you know,
a lot of the things they got wrong in
their future vision were just
compromises over budgets and special
effects, like the the transporter
instead of having shuttles or the they
had no holiday originally because the
cost of trying to do the special effects
for a holiday was just way out of the
budget range of the original series. But
then they added it which is you know
brilliant because it's going to be very
real very soon. And then all the AI
voices are just you know these really
synthetic computerized voices but it's
important for the audience to know who's
speaking and it's it's hard like because
right now AI can easily replicate
Peter's voice perfectly. Um but if you
throw that into your series nobody knows
who's talking. So [clears throat] so all
these compromises are more like media
compromises. So, I'd be really curious
to ask, you know, the the documentary
makers like what which ones are actually
errors in future vision and which ones
are just like, well, look, we're trying
to get the show out the door this week.
What can we do?
>> Well, you'll have a chance to ask those
questions, buddy.
>> Mhm.
>> All right. I'm going to move us to a
conversation about energy and AI. So, uh
let's jump in there. So, this is a tweet
from Elon this week. Um pretty powerful
statement here. Consensus estimates uh
estimate is that 15 gawatts of AI
compute produced in 2027 cannot be
turned on in 2027. So we're producing 15
gawatt worth of GPU chips that can't be
turned on cuz we don't have the energy.
This is harder than just finding power
as you also need to build out all the
transformers, wiring, liquid cooling,
massive chillers and complex networking.
You know, to put this in perspective, 15
gawatts is equivalent to 10 nuclear
plants sitting idle in a single year.
You know, enough energy to power a
midsize American city. So, the point
Elon is making here is that the supply
of transformers, electrical wiring,
liquid coolers, chillers, networking
infrastructure is harder than finding
the electricity uh itself. But one of
the amazing things about Elon is
whenever he sees a, you know, a
roadblock, a barrier of any type, he
jumps in and he, you know, basically
builds it himself. So, let's show the
next tweet that Elon put up this week.
SpaceX and Tesla are each building each
building 100 gawatts per year of solar
production capacity as fast as possible,
but natural gas will still be needed to
supplement and bootstrap solar for
several years. The limiting factor in
natural gas turbine production is
casting the blades and veins. And so
he's going to do that in-house. By doing
this in-house and casting at SpaceX, we
can accelerate natural gas turbines
coming online by up to 18 months, which
is a profound gamecher. So I, you know,
for all the entrepreneurs out there,
this is his playbook, right? Over and
over again. And it's something that's
really important to realize when you see
a roadblock, when something isn't
available, when you get no, then that's
an opportunity. Dave, your your
comments.
>> Well, I mean, at our partner meeting
last week, I was telling the team, look,
if I look at our portfolio companies
that get into the the data center stack,
whether it's energy, transformers, uh,
you know, installation of chips, finding
land, dealing with state government,
every one of those companies is creating
billionaires out of its founders. If I
look at our vertical use case AI
companies, it's a mixed bag. You know, a
lot of them are doing well too, but you
know, slower growth, uh, you know,
trying to get a consumer base for a
video generation app or a apartment
search with AI or whatever. So, it it
the returns on the two sides of that
coin are stark, you know, starkly
different. They're all good. I'm not
saying any of it's not doing well. It's
all doing really, really well, but the
people who cross that chasm and get into
this data center buildout are crushing
it. And there's opportunity at every
level of it from you like somebody who's
connected politically and can get the
land, somebody who can find transformers
overseas and import them, somebody who
can do just architectural design like
deep core design to try and squeeze more
value out of the existing chips or even
legacy chips. All of those things are
huge range of skills, but all those
entrepreneurs are killing it. And it
drives me nuts in the AMA when people
are like, "How can I help? How can I
participate?" and they don't look inside
like go to Tennessee and look inside the
the Colossus and and find the
opportunity and work out from there. But
I was telling the partners on Monday
that like this is just night and day
difference in returns and and you can
see exactly why you know 15 gawatts what
what's that about 10 million idle GPUs.
I mean that's a big fraction of this
year's supply of manufacturing of GPUs
sitting idle in boxes waiting for a way
to get turned on. Massive opportunity.
>> Yeah. You remember uh when we
interviewed him at the beginning of the
year, actually in December, we we played
it in early January. He mentioned then
that Tesla and SpaceX would start
generating solar. So this is the
official announcement, 100 gawatts of
solar for each of them. Uh Alex, this
gets us independent from solar in China.
Hopefully
>> it does. And I I think there are a
couple of perhaps less obvious takes.
One is this indicates to me Elon is very
serious about not just competing in the
Dyson swarm market but also competing in
terrestrial compute. These turbines will
be probably totally useless for LEO or
SSO based orbital data centers but
they're incredibly useful if you're on
the Earth and you're you're competing in
a terrestrial data center buildout. So
point one, I would say this this shows
me that Elon isn't waiting for the Dyson
Swarm uh and Star Mind to to turn on,
which will probably be presumably
primarily solar PV. He's going to
compete terrestrially on the buildout,
which is good news. Second point, I I
think I I think Elon actually would be
one of the first to say the most ironic
solution or the most ironic outcome ends
up being the right one. M
>> I I think Elon is on a trajectory to
become the king of liquid natural gas
which is like the most ironic outcome.
Mr. Mr. Electric everything Mr. uh
electrification becomes the LG king on
the Gulf Coast
>> building his own pipeline right?
>> He's building Star Pipe. Why is he
building Star Pipe? because the SpaceX
all of the SpaceX launches now two Star
bases on the Gulf Coast, one in Texas,
one in Louisiana need natural gas. So,
you can generalize that to say, okay, as
always, like Elon's the an amazing uh
manager of supply chains. He's going to
be consuming all of this LNG, uh,
methane, oxygen, uh, fossil fuels for
the SpaceX launches on now two star
bases, maybe soon more on the Gulf
Coast. inevitably, as long as now he has
a supply of fossil fuels, why not also
leverage that capability just like the
way he was able to pivot all of these
GPUs that were probably intended for
Tesla originally, divert them to XAI,
and then use that to build a hyperscaler
cloud out of XAI to then motivate the
SpaceX IPO through a tortured scheme.
Similarly, my prediction here, I'll
pre-register it, is that Elon,
ironically, becomes the king of liquid
natural gas and fossil fuels in general
in order to force his entire industrial
ecosystem to to basically develop enough
>> electricity and enough infra for the
electricity to power all the terrestrial
data centers.
>> You know, I mean, this is why, you know,
SpaceX is my biggest holding. They are
up and down the stack, you know, from
innermost loop at energy all the way to
orbital compute. Uh, and there's nobody
else even close. I mean, no country is
even close.
>> We have to figure out how to
re-industrialize somehow. And Elon's
teaching us how, I guess.
>> Yeah,
>> that characterization of Elon also
really reconciles with with my
experience, I'm sure, with Peter's
experiences, many many of them with
Elon, where he's not religious about any
of this. He he he does it from first
principles, does the math and then takes
the path forward that just makes sense
regardless of which is politically
convenient. And because he often gets
labeled as being, you know, pro this,
pro that, pro whatever, but he got into
electrification because it just makes
sense mathematically.
>> He loves solving problems. He loves
seeing the biggest problems he can take
on, go back to, you know, first
principles and then create something as
a solution. That's what he does over and
over again. Yeah. So now it turns out to
be LG have liquid natural gas. Alex is
right. He'll be the king of king of
burning fossil fuels to create computar
and solar.
>> And solar. It'll swap out. The LG is
just a stepping stone, right? The chips
can't sit idle.
>> The only place it's not going is
nuclear. All right, I'm going to move us
to a next story around Elon. And uh this
is a heavy Elon episode, but he's said a
lot this past week. Let's talk about
large-scale geoengineering. So this
week, Musk went fully existential,
arguing that switching to sustainable
energy is necessary but insufficient for
humanity survival. His reasoning, quote,
"Extremely severe extinction events
happen every 100 million years or so,
and just switching to sustainable energy
will not be enough to stop them." His
solution, satellites in space that
control temperature and massive
geoengineering will be needed for it
before it's game over. So he describes
what he calls sentient satellites or
solar powered AI satellites that would
sit between the earth and the sun making
continuous small adjustments to incoming
solar radiation to fine-tune earth's
temperature. You know uh so many times
at X-Prize over the last 10 years we
have this thing called visionering. It's
coming up uh se let's see October 15th
16th and 17th. We bring all of our uh
philanthropists all of our brain trust
together. You guys are going to be there
at visionering. Go to xprise.org. or to
learn about visionering. Uh please join
us at that event and we brainstorm and
debate and we discuss what X- prizes we
should design and launch. And the one
I've been pitching for the better part
of a decade I call solar shades. You
know a thermostat for the earth. So
imagine you know between the earth and
the sun you put up these spacecraft that
basically are able to titrate the solar
flux hitting the earth. Uh, and if you
do that, we're able to fine-tune the
temperature on the planet. His
conclusion is, quote, we have about 50
years or so to take action, which should
be more than enough time for the space
satellites to solve any heating problem.
So, uh, Alex,
>> I think,
>> of course, I mean, I I'm a huge fan of
geoengineering. Love geoengineering.
We've been doing it, as we've pointed
out on the pod in the past, we've been
doing it for hundreds of years. We just
haven't been doing it very well. We're
about to start doing it very well. The
the star shade idea, I think, was a
Simpsons episode uh infamously, but I've
been looking for uh again, ironically,
uh startup to fund that would focus on
geoengineering of global weather. Uh I'd
love uh LEO based satellites or in the
alternative terrestrial mirrors to
optimize hurricanes out of existence. If
if you have a hurricane that's about to
hit a coast, wouldn't it be wonderful if
either from the ground or from the air
with AI, you could direct some energy to
steer hurricanes away from populated
coasts? I think this is what Elon is
gesturing at. I think the endgame for
this particular venture, I think he has
like a backlog of all of the
applications of what is space technology
good for. I think for many folks,
orbital data centers came as a surprise,
but it was a big enough boon that he was
able to IPO SpaceX off it. I think he
has a backlog of other things that space
tech could be good for. And I think one
of those items is geoengineering and
weather control. And I completely buy
that with global AI weather models and
enough points of actuation, whether it's
like LEO satellites that are in the
style of reflect orbital, able to divert
some sunlight down to weather patterns
and and focus it to to change the
weather or whether it's what you're
saying, Peter, which is blocking
sunlight. Don't really care. One way or
another, if you have thousands or
millions of low Earth orbit satellites
that can have mirrors able to focus
light or otherwise affect the weather,
then that's a recipe for global weather
engineering. And I think we're going to
get it.
>> Yeah. The the problem is the tragedy of
the commons, right? You know, if you've
got global warming, uh you know, many
nations may not want that, but Russia
may because it opens up the waterways.
And the question is who gets to control
that? Because you're impacting not just
one country or a dozen countries, you're
impacting, you know, a couple hundred
countries.
>> You can trade that. I mean, you can set
up treaties and all of that for for
items for commodities that aren't
tradable. But for the rest, like
municipality A trades with municipality
B for rain. Like they can just you can
have a global weather market. [sighs]
>> Yeah. Alex to trade in the currency of
what should happen. And then you look at
urban planning like urb urban planning
is so simple right compared to to
geoengineering and you look at how
incredibly bad it is like you know like
just traffic jams upon you know it's
just it's just
>> in urban planning most cities weren't
ever designed some cities notoriously
were designed but historically like for
the past few hundred years we've been
massively impacting carbon levels uh and
temperatures and ocean levels on our
planet but not very intentionally. Now
we have the technology or we're about to
have the technology to intentionally
design our world. So let's do it.
>> I agree. I'm I'm optimistic actually
that with AI as a planning partner for
government something will change
radically. But you know the current
process if you said okay we have the
technology for you know for blocking
sunlight or for reflecting sunlight is
actually pretty damn straightforward.
>> Yeah.
>> And so so Elon's exactly right we can
easily start controlling Earth's
temperature uh through satellites. So
then the decision on who controls it and
and what's the right temperature and
like that that's the process that's just
frighteningly broken.
>> Listen, it's always the case until
things get to a drastic level, we don't
take action with a unified voice. I mean
that's been historically the situation.
So we can build these I mean my view of
an X-P prize was doing a demonstrator
right where you are able to demonstrate
that you can build something that's fail
safe. You know, you don't want to cause
an ice age by blocking too much
sunlight, but you want to be able to
titrate it at just the right amount.
>> Optimistic that that, you know, anyone
under the age of say 25 who's AI native
now, uh, is going to be a different
world, a different group of people
governing the world than anyone over the
age of say 70. Uh, it's just a
completely different perspective and I
think it'll cut much more across the
globe. I'm optimistic that that this is
the way it'll evolve because if you look
at things like our story earlier about
sending, you know, a probe off to Alpha
Centauri, that's inspiring to a huge
upand cominging generation. It tends to
unify people all across the world. And
but they're not going to tolerate, I
think, the current divided, indecisive,
slowmoving, ineffective world governance
that we have right now. And so I think
as they grow up as AI natives that are
communicating in every language through
AI across the world, there's a pretty
good chance we'll have a new way of of
managing and deciding these things.
>> I completely agree. And I also think it
there may be a generational angle to
this. I think multiple generations grew
up scared of engineering the physical
world. Maybe it's related to what Tyler
Cowan gestures to as the great
stagnation or WTF happened in 1971.
Maybe. But I I think approximately you
could start counting after World War II
or I think more probably start counting
in the late 1960s, early 1970s silent
spring era when for whatever reason I
think the West in particular decided
that it was allergic to really
intervening with and engineering the
physical world. And that that's like a
half century in my mind lost when we
could have been building fision reactors
and developing them when we could have
started developing early geoengineering
techniques. When we could have stop we
we could have avoided stopping landing
humans on the moon and we just lost 50
years for whatever reason. One can
speculate as to what root cause if any
there is. We just a as a western
civilization we became allergic to
drastic applied physical engineering.
And so I view geoengineering. We talked
in previous pod about rain maker. I to
the extent Elon is now starting to get
interested in geoengineering. I think
this is a return to form and we're we're
trying to put these 50 years of waste
behind us. Well,
God willing or the laws of physics
willing, uh, we're going to figure out
how to take control of our environment
because God knows,
>> uh, doing it randomly has not been
working.
>> Have nanites.
>> Yeah, [laughter] that's true. Nanotech,
you know, we don't talk about
nanotechnology anywhere near enough on
this on this pod. Uh, and it's like
we've been promised it from Eric Drexler
for the last 40 years. Where is it?
liquid liquid nano particles and
>> sorry
over at MIT nano would love to come on
the pod
>> you know assemblers I want assemblers
you know ability to rip you know put
atoms specifically together to build
what you want diamondoid you know
propulsion systems
>> I don't think you actually so 30 second
uh since we don't have sem here I'll
I'll play and insert rant here I I I
don't think
>> we miss you wherever you are
>> we miss you
get through So [laughter] I I don't
think Peter you actually want diamondoid
assemblers. I I do buy that you want
assemblers, but I I think you know I've
had this discussion with Eric Drexler
and others. I don't think you actually
want diamondoid assemblers because the
they're coalently bonded and the
energies are pretty high for doing that.
I think what you actually if if if I
were to be so presumptuous, I think you
want like soft assemblers that look more
like hydrogen bonded and they look more
like biological cells and
>> it's proteins.
>> Exactly. So you want synthetic biology,
you want lipid nanoparticles that go
through diseases.
>> We have So we got nanotechnology.
>> You know, nanotechnology from my
perspective is a little bit different,
right? It's like I have an assembler on
my hand and I I I drop in there and I
say build, you know, build a dozen. I
give you one. And then if I want an
electric Ferrari, I take an assembler
and I drop into the ground and say build
me an electric Ferrari. And it, you
know, it finds the energy which is
ubiquitous. It finds open source, you
know, design specs and it it says, "Hey,
I need a kilogram of titanium and a
kilogram of, you know, whatever." And it
builds it for you um in in speed. I
mean, right now the problem is life. You
know, you drop a oak seed into the
ground and it will take, you know,
multiple years uh to build the oak tree.
The idea of nano assemblers is much
faster, much more capable, much much
more diverse,
>> requiring much more energy. critically
uh and if you want an oak tree over a
very short time scale and I think that's
what's been missing. So my I'll give you
my hot take uh before just wrapping up
the rant. I think it's a problem of
economics. I think economics is actually
why you didn't get your Drexleran nano
assemblers. There's no to my knowledge
no killer business use case that would
merit the energy densities and the
compute densities to justify I want my
nano iron man suit just like I think you
do. But the question is what's the
economic use case? What's the rationale
for having one?
>> Oh gee. But I mean listen the idea I
mean and Ray's talked about this
extensively you know getting real BCI
where you've got uh you know full
[snorts] up connectivity with your
entire brain. Uh and you've got you the
ability to repair everything on a on a
subcellular basis. Uh the vision was
always BCI I'm sorry always going to be
nanotech. I was going to get us that.
Except do you really want diamondoid
nanoobots in your vascular system?
>> Diamond for those watching diamondoid is
basically assembling anything out of
carbon in a diamond hard material and it
doesn't need to be diamondoid but it
needs to be atomically precise.
So I agree with atomic precision but
there are many ways one can achieve
atomic precision either with soft
systems for example like DNA is
atomically precise and you can use DNA
origami and a variety of other synthetic
biological
>> tools. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So my bet is we end up with more
soft nanoobots but we have with LNPS
like the last pandemic was arguably
addressed ultimately with nanotech. It
was like the first nanotech intervention
on a population scale. Welcome to the
health section of Moonshots brought to
you by Fountain Life. You know, AI is
having an outsiz impact on every aspect
of our lives. How we teach our kids, how
we run our companies. It also is having
a huge impact on health, helping you
prevent heart disease. One of the key
things I'm here with Dr. Don Musalem,
our chief medical officer at Fountain.
Heart disease has been personal for you
as well, hasn't it?
>> It really has, Peter. My daughter was
five. My husband died of sudden cardiac
death. And so this is a topic that is
one that I am missiondriven to try to
eradicate. Prevention first and early
detection is absolutely critical. 50% of
people die of heart attacks with no
warning signs.
>> No shortness of breath, no pain, no
nothing.
>> No silent killer.
>> They just don't wake up in the morning.
>> They don't wake up. And so you know AI,
this is our mission to advance science
to try to help to one day democratize
wellness. We know at Fountain Life when
we do this CT angography with AI
analytics, we are actually finding that
88% of people coming in have detectable
coronary arter disease. But Peter,
what's more alarming to me is 23% of
those individuals had soft plaque. This
is the plaque that would not
traditionally be seen on CT looking at
calcium scores alone. And this is the
plaque that we must intervene with with
the multimodal testing we're doing,
including diagnostic laboratory studies
partnered with healthy lifestyle
recommendations.
>> So listen, make sure you understand
what's going on inside your body
genetically, metabolically, and
cardiovascularly. You can know and it's
your obligation to know. So check it out
at fountainlife.com/peter
to find out more and really make sure
that you're the CEO of your own health.
All right, back to the episode. All
right, I'm going to move us to our our
last story block on space. So, uh,
President Trump this week announced that
NASA is working on nuclearpowered
interplanetary spacecraft that will
launch on a mission to Mars in 2028. Uh,
he promised a massive American Starfleet
and said the ships would be among the
first of those that would ultimately get
us to Mars. That space travel is almost
its goal is making space travel almost
as common as ocean travel. Okay, let's
watch this video uh from 3 days ago.
>> NASA has already begun to work on the
first ever nuclearpowered interplanetary
spacecraft which will launch in 2028 on
a mission to Mars. It's coming so
incredible. They have to go nuclear
because they have unlimited essentially
unlimited fuel. You don't have to fill
up the tanks every so many miles, right?
It's incredible. This ship will be among
the first of what will ultimately be a
massive American starfleet, making space
travel almost as common as ocean travel
today.
>> All right. Uh we heard about it from
administrator Jared Isaacman. So nuclear
propulsion getting us to Mars instead of
in 7 months, getting us there in one or
two months. Shorter transit means less
radiation exposure, fewer supplies
needed, and dramatically lower mission
costs. uh a nuclear Mars ship in 2028,
two years from now. Can't wait. But
here's my question, guys. You know, Elon
wants Starship to be the mechanism that
gets us to Mars. And he's projected sort
of, you know, originally 2026 was a
projection. Now, uh you know, Tesla,
Optimus on Mars in 2028. Is this a race?
>> Of course, it's a race.
>> It's a race.
>> Like getting out of the gravity well is
definitely a race. Once you're out of
the gravity well though, it's a
free-for-all. I think I don't think it's
a race.
>> NASA versus SpaceX.
>> Interesting.
>> SpaceX versus Blue Origin versus Rocket
Lab versus dot dot dot versus China. Of
course.
>> Yeah.
>> So, uh, you know, listen, nuclear
propulsion should have been here a long
time ago, and people were just always
concerned. Finally, we've got spacecraft
with a 99.99%,
you know, reliability. And people have
been worried about, you know, launching
something. It used to be pickers sitting
out out front of Kennedy Space Center
whenever a, you know, a thermal nuclear
unit was being launched on a deep deep
space mission. That's not happening
anymore. Thank God. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Deoupled two things there. You
know, getting out of the gravity well is
methane, but it's the reusable rocket
that's made that suddenly viable. Elon
cracked the code on it, but now
everyone's going to copy it, including
the Chinese, including NASA. But the
reusability is everything. But once
you're out of the gravity, well, the,
you know, the xenon ion engines, uh,
we're just waiting. And, you know, AI is
the big unlock on designing all this. We
heard that earlier in the pod, too. So,
the explosion of things operating in
space is going to come from that double
whammy of concurrently we can get out of
the gravity well cheaply and we have AI
as a design tool. I mean, so it's this
is not science fiction all of a sudden.
This is really going to happen because
of that confluence of two concurrent uh
events.
>> Yeah. Turns out the singularity isn't
just vibes after all. And I I I would
also note I mean at the very end of the
president's remarks, did you hear him
say we're getting an American Starfleet?
>> I love that.
>> Like this is right out of Star Trek. We
we are so catching up with Star Trek and
Star Trek so needs to reinvent itself to
stay ahead of where we are.
>> Yeah. Well, I I think nuclear tugs,
right? We'll probably use Starship to
get people into Earth orbit, uh probably
to the moon, but a a nuclear tug that is
able to get us back and forth to Mars or
get us out to the outer planets. Yeah,
>> that particle accelerator the size of a
toaster is just like just insane. And
that's coming from a tiny little R&D
budget. That's just awesome. That shows
you what's possible. 10 million tokens.
The related story here is that four days
ago, uh, the president chartered the
United States Space Academy, modeled
after West Point and the Naval Academy
to educate and train engineer,
scientists, and astronauts who will crew
the Starfleet. Jared Isaacman, the
astronaut, entrepreneur who serves as
our amazing NASA administrator, called
the academy a transformational step. So
now I've got a target for my kids if
they want to go. Starfleet Academy is
here.
>> Starfleet Academy is here. remember. So,
this was actually when we were
soliciting questions to ask Jared when
he was on the pod. One of the questions
other than the UAP question I was being
asked the most is, "Ask Jared, if I'm
like an average American civilian, how
can I get a job on the moon?" And so, I
I posed that question to him. You you
may recall during our interview with
him, and now we have the answer.
Administrator IsaacMen is being put in
charge. I mean, they're not literally
calling it Starfleet Academy, but they
might as well. He's being put in charge
of Starfleet Academy and we're getting
Starfleet Academy. It would be called US
Space Academy, but it's Starfleet
Academy. It'll probably be if reading
the tea leaves probably be in Texas, not
San Francisco. But I'll settle for for
Texas for having a Starfleet Academy in
a year or two.
>> Amazing. All right, gentlemen. Shall we
take on a few AMA questions?
>> Sure, let's do it.
>> All right. Uh Dave, your choice.
>> All right, I'm going to start at the
top. How do you reconcile the vision of
abundance where goods and services
become free or inexpensive with frontier
companies projecting trillions in
revenue? That's from Rusty K200. Okay,
Rusty K. Uh, look, Elon said it right.
You know, we're talking about uh 10x
growth of the GDP in under 10 years,
which, you know, is starting to feel
like not only real, but maybe even a
lowball estimate. Uh so the amount of
abundance, you know, you you could you
can measure it in dollars and in uh we
might have massive deflation, which is a
point that Elon made on that podcast,
but regardless, the amount of of
abundant stuff available to everyone is
through the roof. And so, yeah, there's
plenty of room for the foundation model
companies to make trillions of dollars
and still have lots and lots of stuff
going out to everybody on the planet,
too. It's just a much much bigger
overall economy.
>> Yep, agreed. We'll see if Elon's
projections of, you know, tripledigit
growth of the GDP in 5 years hold. We'll
ask him on our production our
predictions episode. Uh, Alex.
>> All right, I'll pick question number
four, which asks, "One of the biggest
complaints about data centers is how
noisy they are. What's the solution for
that?" And this is from Niels 9208.
Okay, so a few thoughts. I talked to my
newsletter about how data center
companies are now hiring folks who
specialize in acoustics to do noise
measurement studies to actually measure
this and argue in some cases against
municipalities regarding exactly how
noisy the data centers are. So the the
superficial glib answer is data centers
are going to migrate to space and in
space no one can hear you scream and in
space also no one can complain that your
data center is noisy. So that that's the
the superficial answer. The the less
obvious answer, I think, is a number of
years ago, Apple patented, I think, a
very clever solution for how to minimize
fan noise. Apple's focus was on the
noise from fans in laptops and desktops,
which are also noisy. But critically,
the noise from fans isn't white noise.
It's not spread spectrum because there
the the the frequency response, the the
impulse response is determined by the
shape of the blade. So, Apple came up
with and patented at least one, maybe
more than one clever solution for
asymmetric blades in fans that would
smooth out the noise spectrum, make it
flatter and whiter, and as a result, if
the noise coming out of a fan is whiter,
it sounds a lot like it just blends into
the background. It's not doesn't feel as
noisy. So my my clever solution here,
uh, Apple, I know you're not in the data
center business, but you should license
your clever desktop and laptop fan
patents to the data center industry so
that data centers can benefit with white
noise.
>> Is it just that or is it also, you know,
natural gas turbines making a lot of
noise?
>> Well, the turbine turbines are the same.
It's it's fans. It's things going around
in loops that are symmetric creating
nonwhite noise. You called color noise.
So, if we can switch basically
decolorize the noise from data centers,
uh, keeping everything else the same,
basically change the shape of the fans
of of the turbines and the things going
around, that should smooth out the
spectrum and make them seem a lot less
noisy.
>> All right, number three. Ryan Boington
7941 says, "Could abandoned mills be
repurposed as data centers to revitalize
struggling towns?" And yes, I mean the
fact of the matter is any struggling
town, whether they have mills or don't
have mills, can cut a deal with a data
center and negotiate properly. Tell them
that you want them to guarantee, you
know, a rate cut on energy. Tell them
that you want to guarantee schools and,
you know, uh, you know, better police
and fire departments. You know, you've
got you've got the key negotiating
position. Ask for what you want. So
that's my answer for number three. I
>> have a case study in that too. You know,
Rob Fischer from here went off to start
or co-found provocative, which is a data
center in Somerville,
>> which is an opportunity zone,
desperately needed the business. But I
was asking him like, why in this
location? And he said, it's an old
carpet mill, which is why there's a huge
amount of electrical power that comes
into this particular block. So, we just
repurposed it as a data center. It's
much less polluty and noisy than a
carpet mill was, and much better for the
local economy. So, it clearly does work.
>> Alex, you want to take number two?
>> Sure. Two asks, NVIDIA's biggest
vulnerability is supposed to be TSMC,
but isn't the bigger one that four of
its largest customers are now shipping
their own silicon? This is asked by
Haymont05.
Yes and no. And yes and no. I I think
Nvidia has strengths as well, not just
vulnerabilities. It has accumulated an
enormous amount of capital. It's the
most valuable corporation in the world.
and pretty publicly now is using that
capital to buy its own supply chain and
its own customer chain. Uh so in many
cases Nvidia has weaponized its capital
very publicly to basically purchase
loyalty of customers. So yes, some of
its customers are vertically integrating
the Frontier Labs uh as as Dave would
say the the Magna Mopstas all are
developing their own custom silicon.
True. on the other hand, they're all
purchasing still from Nvidia. It's not
like they're able to wean themselves off
overnight. And at the same time, I think
the bigger question is Nvidia able to
wean itself off of TSMC, which is the
first part of this question. And I think
the the solution there is yes and what
everyone is or almost everyone is
sleeping on. I would predict that Nvidia
is in some back room somewhere striking
a deal with Elon to be the anchor tenant
for Terraab and Terraab ends up being
the the swap, the last minute plot twist
substitution for TSMC.
>> Couldn't agree with you more on that
one. Uh Dave,
>> I'll take number seven. Will AI's
capacity for knowledge keep expanding
like the human mind or will it require
brute force? That's from QC for life.
Quality control for life. Um, great
question. I've been thinking about this
since I was a teenage kid. And, uh,
we're about to find out. It's it's very
likely that it can expand to infinity or
near infinity or or, you know, levels we
can't even comprehend very quickly from
where we are right now. Um, it's going
to improve its own chips. It's going to
improve its own software. It's going to
run thousands, maybe a million times
faster very soon. And then it's going to
learn and learn and learn. I think it
was Ilia Sudskver who said the AI just
wants to learn. So it's going to absorb
all information that's ever been
produced in no time and then be starved
for more information and it'll start
asking us to produce tests or
experiments or whatever to keep feeding
the great machine. Uh nobody can predict
what exactly will come out of that a
year from today or two years from today.
But it's going to be something we've
never experienced before and a whole new
world.
>> Nice. Alex, over to you. I think I have
to take question number five which asks
if you induce rainfall in one region
could that reduce rainfall in areas
downwind and this is from Jim Plamund
637. Yes, I I do think so. I I think
water to first order water is conserved
on this planet and so yes if if there's
water in the atmosphere and it falls in
one place presumably to first order that
reduces the water that can fall downwind
of that. I think the question behind the
question is, isn't that a problem? And I
think the answer is no. I think we will
trade atmospheric effects. We will trade
weather. It'll be a vibrant market. And
some municipalities don't want rainfall
and some do. I think the bigger question
is what happens when you have the
capability via global planetary scale AI
weather models for a region on one side
of the planet to trade weather with one
on the other. not just downwind but one
could imagine a case where a desert say
at um Sahara is able to trade with
somewhere in North America trade
precipitation to regine the Sahara. I
think that is possible with a suitable
weather control system and good enough
planetary scale AI models and I I think
there'll just be a vibrant market for
weather.
>> All right. Uh number six. Should every
robo taxi, humanoid delivery robot and
drone broadcast a verifiable passport
showing its operator ensure and its
limits? asks at at AI Mama protocol. So
AI Mama great question and I think the
answer is yes. I think every one of
these autonomous vehicles is going to be
uh needing for regulatory purposes as
well as insurance purposes needing to uh
have an identifier uh and probably an
off switch as well. So, um, let's see.
AI Mama asked a second question, number
eight. Do you want to take that, Alex?
>> Sure. If AI disproportionately benefits
those with time and capital, how does
that abundance reach caregivers,
disabled people, and displaced workers?
I actually think this question is
identical. If you remove AI from the
sentence entirely, you could equally
well say if capital uh or or something
substantially equivalent to capital, if
capital benefits those with capital, how
does that abundance reach everyone else?
I think the answer is the same. I think
ideally,
not just ideally, in practice as well,
we're going to be a much much wealthier
civilization in a few years. and the
nature of caregiving, the nature of
treatment of disabilities, the nature of
work is going to be transformed beyond
recognition. So I I think asking how I
think sort of the the questions framed
almost uh asking asking the question of
trickle down economics maybe hoping that
I'm going to say something about trickle
down. I'm not going to say anything
about trickle down beyond just
mentioning it. I actually think the
question is analogous to asking in the
1950s or 1960s, when are American
housewives going to get their atomic
vacuum cleaners? It's not even wrong.
We're going to cure the disabilities.
We're going to solve all the top 5,000
diseases. We're going to change the
nature of work. And so many of these
classes that would otherwise naively
benefit superficially from trickle down
economics of capital or from AI are just
going to be transformed beyond
recognition. and we're going to actually
solve the root problem.
>> It's the abundance thesis. We demonetize
and democratize.
>> Uh, absolutely. And so it's, you know,
this sort of reminds me of the wealth
gap conversation where you've got
trillionaires living forever on Mars and
the poorest people back on Earth. And
you know, I get that question every time
I'm on stage and people say, "Isn't the
wealth gap growing?" And I say, "Yes, it
is. But what's also moving is the floor.
And if we can move the floor for every
single man, woman, and child on the
planet, so everyone has access to all
the food, water, energy, healthcare,
education that they want. If they're
trillionaires working on Mars, that's
fine. But we're living in a much more
peaceful world when every mother knows
their children has access to, you know,
abundance. And so, yeah.
>> Did you see, Peter, that reporting that
Leopold Dashen Brener promised his
fiance an entire galaxy?
>> Uh, which one did he buy for her? I I
don't think he actually got around to
purchasing it. I I think situational
awareness had a bit of a hiccup that may
have prevented him from purchasing a
galaxy, but I I do think, you know, when
when Leopold is promising galaxies to
his fiance, it's a bit of a wealth gap,
I suppose. But it's one that with enough
technology presumably that's under the
category of good problem to happen.
>> Well, you know, we do have two trillion
uh in the known universe and so
everybody could probably, you know,
promise a few uh million to their
fiances if they wanted. How many
>> you get a galaxy and you get a galaxy.
>> Uh all right everybody, thank you for
watching us. Uh See, we miss you buddy.
Uh
>> get through TSA.
>> Yeah, we'll see you next time. All
right.
>> Entire episode he's been in a line.
That's that's kind of funny.
>> Uh take care all. Be well.
>> Thanks, Peter.